<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A free-vvill offering, or, a Pillar of praise with a thankfull remembrance for the receit of mercies, in a long voyage, and happy arrivall. First preached in Fen-Church, the 7 of September, 1634. now published by the author, Samuel Hinde.</title>
            <title>Free-will offering.</title>
            <author>Hinde, Samuel, fl. 1634.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03390</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13511</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115210</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850429</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850429</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15631</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03390)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15631)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1275:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A free-vvill offering, or, a Pillar of praise with a thankfull remembrance for the receit of mercies, in a long voyage, and happy arrivall. First preached in Fen-Church, the 7 of September, 1634. now published by the author, Samuel Hinde.</title>
                  <title>Free-will offering.</title>
                  <author>Hinde, Samuel, fl. 1634.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 73 [i.e. 89], [7] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Harper,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1634.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A sermon.</note>
                  <note>Last leaf blank?.</note>
                  <note>Page 89 misnumbered 73.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15631:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15631:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15631:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15631:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Free-VVill Offering,</hi> OR, <hi>A Pillar of Praiſe,</hi> With a thankfull remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance for the receit of mercies, in a long voyage, and happy arrivall.</p>
            <p>Firſt Preached in <hi>Fen-Church,</hi> the 7 of <hi>September,</hi> 1634. now publiſhed by the Author, SAMVEL HINDE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Exod. 17.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Write this for a memoriall in a Booke, and rehearſe it in the eares of <hi>Ioſhua.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by THOMAS HARPER. 1634.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15631:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15631:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL <hi>Sir</hi> WILLIAM COVRTEN Knight, The Author dedicates both him ſelfe, and labours.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I were a Iudge inſtead of a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour, it ſhould be my charge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of my advice, to charge them that are rich in this world,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.17.</note> that they truſt not in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine
<pb facs="tcp:15631:4"/> riches, but in the living God. Nor could ſuch a charge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne any (for ought I know) more, than your ſelfe, on whom the God of bleſsing hath heap't ſuch afflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and abundance, as if both Sea and Land, the Chriſtian and the heathen world had conſpired to empty themſelues into your coffers and ware-houſes.</p>
            <p>He ſaid it that will maintaine it, <hi>To whom much is given,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 12.48.</note> 
               <hi>of them much ſhall be required:</hi> Your en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gagements to the God of Heaven are neither common, nor ordinary, but as if ſingled out for bleſsings, you have received a <hi>Benjamins</hi> portion above many others of your brethren.<note place="margin">Gen 43.34.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I know: the world knows, that you hide not theſe talants in a nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin,<note place="margin">Lu. 19.20.</note> thouſands are bettered by their improvement, your imployment.</p>
            <p>The following Manuell or En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiridion,
<pb facs="tcp:15631:4"/> will onely advertiſe you (not as if you wanted better diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline) that amongſt all other your tranſactions and tranſmutations, you, returne to the Caeſar of hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ven his tributary due of praiſe and thankfulneſſe, from whoſe liberall hand you have received ſuch am<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple teſtifications of favour and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficence.</p>
            <p>This Pyramis of praiſe, this new erected pillar ſerues for no other end,<note place="margin">Statuae Mercurii in competis &amp; triviis, quae certis indiciis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexo viate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, iter o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendebant A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. Gel.</note> but like the Statues of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury,</hi> to direct every traveller and voyager, or any elſe that are capable of mercies, to the wayes of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, and to divert them from the paths of that Satanicall ſinne, ingratitude: What was once plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in your eares, is now preſented to your eyes, favour it with ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, reade it with diligence, follow it with conſcience, and the God of mercy give unto you what
<pb facs="tcp:15631:5"/> bleſsings the booke can containe, or the Author wiſh, for this life or for a better.</p>
            <p>It was no diſhonour to the great Peere and Lord of Syriah,<note place="margin">2. King. 5.13.</note> 
               <hi>Naa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> that he liſtened to the advice of his ſervants.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Solvit inops diti Craeſo quod debuit Irus. Owen. Epigr. lib. un. ep. <hi>62.</hi>
               </note> Rich <hi>Croeſus</hi> diſdained not to receive a debt from poore <hi>Irus.</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you alſo of this my <hi>Free-will Offering,</hi> which, together with my ſelfe, is juſtly devoted to your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and patronage. Twas con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in the wombe of the vaſt Ocean, tis my Firſt-borne, which I can father on none but your ſelfe, from whoſe influence next under God, I received what I have, or can preſent unto you.</p>
            <p>The injury were too publicke if I ſhould be too tedious,<note place="margin">Horat.</note> 
               <hi>Cum tot ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtineas, ac tanta negotia ſolus, in publica commoda peccem ſi lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go ſermone morer tua tempora, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15631:5"/>
            <p>In briefe then I commit this to you, and you to God, wiſhing what happineſſe or honour you do or can wiſh unto your ſelfe, or ſucceſſefull progenie, health to your perſon, bleſsing to your endeavours, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to your enterpriſes, ſecuritie to your body, ſalvation to your ſoule. So prayes he that doth prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer and promiſe obedience to your laudable</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Commands and injunctions, SAMUEL HINDE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15631:6"/>
            <head>The Author to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader, in the peruſall of the following leaves, thou ſhalt have ſome tryall both of thy patience and judgement. My abſence from the Preſſe, with ſome delinquency of the tranſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, occaſioned divers errours, which either thy judgement may rectifie, or thy patience diſpence with. I endeavoured to purge it from ſome, which thou ſhalt finde amended in the cloſure of the booke. Let thy ayme be directed to the matter, not the words, 'twill bring God moſt honour, thy ſelfe moſt benefit.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy faithfull friend and Monitor, <hi>S. H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15631:6"/>
            <head>A PILLAR OF PRAISE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 107.23</hi>
                  </bibl> They that goe downe to the Sea in ſhips, and doe their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in great waters,</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 107.24</hi>
                  </bibl> Theſe men ſee the workes of the Lord, and his wonders in the deepe, &amp;c.</q>
               <q>☞ <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 107.30</hi>
                  </bibl> Then are they glad,<note place="margin">☜ Text.</note> becauſe they be at reſt, and ſo hee bringeth them to the haven where they would be.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 107.31</hi>
                  </bibl> Oh that men would therfore praiſe the Lord for his goodneſſe, and declare the wonders that hee doth for the children of men.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:15631:7"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſonne of <hi>Ieſſe,</hi> and ſweet ſinger of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall parts of this Pſalme, ſummons up divers ſorts of debtors to the King of heauen to diſcharge their obligations, and make their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance in the Courts of the King of glory, there to pay their vowes and his dues of praiſe and thankfulneſſe. Neither doth the Prophets ſummons concerne a few, or is the tribute of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly <hi>Caeſar</hi> to bee leuied of the remnants and out-caſts of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> both are as large as the taxation of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 2.5</note> wherein all the world was taxed. None that's cloath'd with humane fleſh can free themſelues from theſe obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, except they can ſhuffle themſelues out of the number of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15631:7"/> Prince or people, trauellers by Land, voyagers by Sea, be they Sea men or Land men, Sicke men or Sound men, Free men or Bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaues, Rich or Poore: Let their perſons be whom they will, their qualifications how they will, their conditions what they will, all are here wiſhed and warned, ſent for and ſummoned to praiſe the Lord for his goodneſſe, and to declare the wonders that he, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But in theſe particular verſes of this Pſalme which I haue ſingled out from the reſt, like a Deere from the Heard: the Prophet of God, and the God of Prophets, addreſſe themſelves to ſuch one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as goe downe into the Sea in ſhips,<note place="margin">Verſe 23.</note> and doe their buſineſſe in great waters. Thoſe painefull voyagers as compaſſe their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings and your liuings in the fearefull flouds, and are daily
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15631:8"/> ſpectators of his works and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the deepe, being brought to the haven where they would be, are here excited to teſtifie their thankfulneſſe, by the performance of a double duty, to praiſe the Lord for his goodneſſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the wonders that hee doth for the children of men:</p>
            <p>This is the Prophets wiſh, and Sea mans obligation; <hi>O that men would therefore praiſe the Lord, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Brethren and beloved in the Lord, I cannot exclude my ſelfe from the number of ſuch whoſe obligations are infinite to the God of heaven for his favourable protection both by ſea and land. I dare not like thoſe unthankfull Lepers, ſmother the mercy of an omnipotent God and beneficent Saviour, either in ſilence or ingra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titude.<note place="margin">Luk 17.17</note> Let thoſe other Lepers of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15631:8"/> 
               <hi>Samaria</hi> ſhould riſe up in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt mee, who ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves;<note place="margin">2 King 7.9</note> 
               <hi>This is a day of good tidings, wee doe not well to hold our peace; If we tarry till the morning light, ſome miſchiefe will befall us; now therefore come that wee may goe and tell the Kings houſhold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It were a piece of impardona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſacriledge to monopolize or ingroſſe the divine Elixar of my Maſters and my Makers mercies and miracles, workes and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, that I have had experience of in forraigne and farre diſtant Climats, Counties, Kingdomes, Ilands, Provinces, Nations, Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Languages. Since then that God the Father requires no more of me than God the Sonne did of the diſpoſſeſſed Demoniacke, <hi>Mark.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Goe and tell what great things the Lord hath done
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15631:9"/> for thee,</hi> I were unworthy of my tongue if I ſhould not ſpeake to you, of your eares if you ſhould not heare what ſhall be delivered. May the God of heaven there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore open my lips,<note place="margin">Mark. 1.17.34.</note> and my mouth ſhall ſhew forth his praiſe, ſay <hi>Ephphata</hi> to your eares, and they ſhall be opened for the wonders of the King of glory to enter in.</p>
            <p>In theſe words that I have read, and you have heard, there is an exact mixture and accurate compoſure of Dangers, Mercies, and Duties; theſe three are wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and platted in the Text, and are the three Tabernacles of my meditation: here I build one for God, another for you, a third for my ſelfe, and ſuch elſe as it doth concerne. Here is dangers of ſuch as goe downe into the deepe, Mercies of him that made the Sea and all that therein is, Duties for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15631:9"/> ſuch as have received theſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and eſcapt theſe dangers, and are brought to the haven where they would be. Heaven, earth, and waters rowle and tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble up the billowes of the Text, the woofe and warpe whereof is ſpun both of courſe and fine threed.<note place="margin">Exra 8.16. Exod. 36.1 1 Cor 3.16</note> It would require the skill of <hi>Iarib</hi> and <hi>Elnathan,</hi> men of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; the hand and loome of ſome <hi>Aholiab</hi> and <hi>Bezaleel,</hi> to make it fit worke for the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of the Lord, for the Temple of God, which Temple yee are; that while you heare of theſe dangers, ye may be brought to feare and awfulneſſe: of theſe mercies, yee may be drawne to practiſe thankfulneſſe, of theſe duties ye may be woed to ſervice and obedience.</p>
            <p>It wants not what skill I could beſtow upon it according to my
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15631:10"/> talant and ability, and my time and preſent opportunity, of which I may ſay as <hi>Philip</hi> of the five loaves and two fiſhes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Alas, what are theſe amongſt ſo many. Alas, what are theſe my meditations, theſe water-works, not able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the ſhadows of that divine Majeſtie they do adore, and to which they are dedicated. Yet they ſhould be ſeaſonable, they have croſſed many briniſh bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows and waves of ſalt water, and to you they ſhould be acceptable. For as amongſt you I preached my <hi>Vale</hi> and long farewel, ſo now by divine providence am I brought againe once more upon this holy mount,<note place="margin">The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion day.</note> to ſalute you with my <hi>primum ſalve,</hi> firſt ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: what you can conceive not to be ſeaſonable in regard of your time and meeting. You may
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15631:10"/> freely correct it, t'will ſhew part of your judgement, which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to be ſutable in reſpect of my time and arrivall, you may fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably accept it as part of my love. Incline therefore your eares to the tenor of the following Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſie, the arrant is Gods, the task is mine, the uſe is yours.</p>
            <p>Let your pious acceptance and patient attention, be as Midwives to aſſiſt me in the delivery of theſe three dangers, mercies, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that ſtruggle in the wombe of my text, like the quarrelling twinnes that deſcended from the loynes of <hi>Iſaac</hi> from the bowels of <hi>Rebeckah.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 25.22</note> The rough and hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <hi>Eſau</hi> comes firſt to view. Ile firſt ſpeake of the dangers,<note place="margin">Ioh. 2.9.</note> reſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ving the other as the Bridegroom did his beſt wine untill the laſt.</p>
            <p>They that go downe into the ſea expoſe themſelves unto a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15631:11"/> that like the mace of <hi>Neptune</hi> is three-forked.<note place="margin">Danger threefold.</note> All voyagers are lyable to a triple danger, of the Sea, of the enemies in the Sea, of the enemies on the ſhore after their arrivall.</p>
            <p>In any or all theſe three kindes was there never more danger than now ſince <hi>Noahs</hi> Dove was pilot unto <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke,<note place="margin">Gen. 8.8.</note> or ſince <hi>Saturne</hi> the King of <hi>Greete</hi> did firſt finde out the Art of <hi>Navigation.</hi> The way of a ſhip in the Sea is one of thoſe foure things that prou'd a paradox to puzſle and <hi>non-plus</hi> the wiſe and great King <hi>Solomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 30.9.</note> and thouſands more ſince his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution.</p>
            <p>He that commits himſelfe to the cuſtody of a three incht plank (for there's no more betweene death and us) had need to ſay with <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 108.1.</note> 
               <hi>My heart is ready, O Lord, my heart is ready:</hi> He had
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15631:11"/> need to be ready for proſperitie, ready for adverſity, ready for li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, ready for ſlavery, ready for the ſtormes, tempeſts of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, ready for the calmes and favourable aire of mercy He muſt look to be a ſharer in the firſt,<note place="margin">Phil 4.11.</note> he may hope to be partaker of the laſt.</p>
            <p>They that go downe into the deepe ſhall ſee a Sea whoſe bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows bellow, whoſe ſurges ſwell, raging with tempeſts, roaring with whirlwinds, and be at once terrified with fearefull thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claps, dazled with terrible lighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, amazed with ayerie fires and apparitions, aſtoniſhed with eruptions and evaporations from the furnaces of heaven, with the clouds, thoſe bottles of heaven, that ſometimes emptie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in ſuch violence as if they threatned another deluge. With
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15631:12"/> thoſe windes that come from the treaſuries and hollow concaves of the earth, which as is let looſe for vengeance, like ſome accurſed bandogge, are more fierce for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer cohibitions. Theſe, beſides many other ſad apparences, are they lyable to, that go downe into the deepe, which oftentimes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright them worſe then the ghoſt of <hi>Brutus</hi> did him in his diſmall and nocturnall viſion.<note place="margin">Plutarch. Cher.</note> Now ſuch as are humbled with theſe judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, amazed with theſe won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, aſtoniſhed with theſe ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, affrighted with theſe appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritions, can never diſrelliſh the offers of mercy in ſuch deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, they cannot but praiſe the Lord for his goodneſſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his wonders that he doth for the children of men.</p>
            <p>I lived to ſee which now I live to declare and memorate, all the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15631:12"/> foure elements in a combuſtion,<note place="margin">Pſa. 118 17</note> uproare and confuſion, as if they had beene to have beene reduced to their former chaos.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Frigida pugnabant calidis,<note place="margin">Ovid. lib. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Met:</note> hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentia ſiccis,</l>
               <l>Mollia cum duris, ſine pondere habentia pondus.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Having paſſed the dangerous and ſtrait gulph of the danger,</l>
               <l>Incidit in Scyllam qui vult vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare Charybdim:<note place="margin">Ovid. in Loc.</note>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Not farre diſtant from the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacrian</hi> or <hi>Sicilian</hi> ſhore we ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led neare an Iſland that burnes like mount <hi>Sinai,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Earth.</note> yet not conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with thoſe blaſts of fire, which proceed from Mines of brimſtone by which they are nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed. The terrible and ſulphu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious flames do pierce the ayre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove,<note place="margin">Fire.</note> that in the day time it ſeemes to be covered with ſmoke, in the night with fire. The ayrie
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15631:13"/> and tempeſtuous windes above,<note place="margin">Ayre.</note> enraged the billows and ſurges of the Sea below,<note place="margin">Water.</note> that as ſaid the Poet:
<q>
                  <note place="margin">Ovid de Pont.</note>Iam iam tacturos ſidera ſumma putes.</q> So ſaid the Prophet, ſo ſay I, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we were lifted up to the heavens, and ſometimes caſt downe againe unto the deepe, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie element a meſſenger of death; The fire flaming, the earth ſmok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the ayre ſtorming, the water raging;<note place="margin">Pſa. 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.5.</note> as if all the foundations of the earth had beene out of courſe. The envelloped clouds deſcended round about us in ſhouts terrible to each beholder into the water, the water aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the clouds, and as a weaker veſſell yeelded to their violence. The fire burnt in the bowels of the earth, and the earth uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of reſiſtance ſent forth flaſhes
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15631:13"/> and flames of fire and brimſtone, as if Hell had no other chimney but <hi>Strumbelo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Strumbelo, Aetna <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, mount Soma or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſuvia puteoli all burning mountaines.</note> and the adjacent mountaines to vent her ſmoke. Theſe things for commonneſſe and familiarity to ſome Marriners the oftner they are ſeene the leſſe they are regarded. But ſome freſh-water ſpectator beholding them in their terrour, would think per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps as little of preaching in a Church of <hi>England,</hi> as ever did <hi>Ionah</hi> in the ſtreets of <hi>Ninive,</hi> when the ſea was his death, the fiſh was his death, the winde and waves his death: <q>Preſentemque intentant omnia mortem.<note place="margin">Virg in Luc.</note>
               </q> Yet that God that ſet <hi>Ionah</hi> a ſhore upon the borders and liſts of <hi>Syriah,</hi> hath brought us alſo to the Haven where we would be. <hi>Oh that men would therefore praiſe the Lord, and declare the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15631:14"/> wonders that he hath done for us the children of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe and all other dangers to which Seamen are ſubject have their end and uſe: For as the pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and mulct of <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> did ſerue to adorne the altars of <hi>Iupiter:</hi> ſo the miſeries and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of ſuch adventurers do work together for the beſt to them that love God,<note place="margin">Ro. 8.28.</note> and are called of his purpoſe. Here's ſome honour to adorne the altars of the God of heaven. For as ſtormes do purge the ayre above, ſo they do or ſhould purifie mens hearts below. For now if ever the Marriners will deprecate their Dieties, and call upon <hi>Ionah</hi> to call upon his God.<note place="margin">Ion. 1.5.6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now if ever the Diſciples will awake their Saviour with a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Maſter, ſave us, we periſh.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 8.26.</note> Now every <hi>Turke</hi> betakes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15631:14"/> him to his ſacrifice, every Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an unto his prayers. Even ſuch as allow not or approve not of a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanie aſhore would quickly learne to ſay and pray, From lightening and thunder from ſtormes and tempeſts, from violence of winde and waves: God Lord deliver us.</p>
            <p>The ſoundeſt heart will diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh this bitter Colloquintida, and quake to be fed with this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſavoury Hemlocke, though but for a few dayes or houres, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſtormes are once blowne over will preferre the caſe of a Chriſtian to the wealth of an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rab or ſavage <hi>Indian:</hi>
               <q>Quid maris extremos Arabas ditantia &amp; Indos.<note place="margin">Horace in loc.</note>
               </q> I, and conclude with <hi>Meander:</hi>
               <q>Satius eſſe pauperem in terra vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, quam divitem mari ſe committere:</q> It's ſafer to live a poore man on
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15631:15"/> ſhore, than a rich man at Sea.</p>
            <p>Neither are we more ſubject to the violence of windes at ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times then to variety at other:<note place="margin">Aul. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. li <hi>2</hi> c. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> at night we ſayle <hi>Vento Iapige</hi> with <hi>Virgils</hi> Weſterne winde;<note place="margin">Act. 27.14</note> ere mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night troubled with <hi>Pauls</hi> tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous <hi>Euroclydon</hi> which blew and bluſtered at midnight; ere morning,<note place="margin">Virg. Aen. <hi>1</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Validus iactaverit au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in alto,</hi> turned with a Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne and after that a Northerne gale, tis poſſible to ſee them and many more blow all at once ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Poeticall deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, where each ſtrives to get the maſtery: <note place="margin">Virg.</note> 
               <hi>Vna Euruſque Notuſque ruunt, Creberque procellis Affri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor yet more troubled either with violence of winds or variety then a third time with want and ſcarcity. After heaven had ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to frown and lower, ſhe now
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15631:15"/> doth laugh and ſmile at our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer troubles and preſent helpleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Now we have a breathing time, and our former ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes be becalm'd. It proves to many the increaſe of worſe, who lye for want of winde in ſight of their port but cannot come at it: Like <hi>Moſes</hi> in the ſight of <hi>Canaan</hi> but could not come neare it. The firſt makes them a trouble to themſelues which is ſtormes of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance; the laſt which is the calmes of want do make them a booty and purchaſe for roving and ranging Pirats,<note place="margin">2. Danger of the ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mie in the Sea.</note> which is but the ſecond part of Danger, at firſt propoſed.</p>
            <p>One woe is paſt,<note place="margin">Revel. 9.12</note> and now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold another woe is at hand:<note place="margin">Sicut unda impellitur unda, Ov.</note> I two more woes doe follow it as one wave doth another.</p>
            <p>If there were no more woes or danger in the Sea then the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15631:16"/> of our enemies, it were enough to make a voyage miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: No day in the week, or ſcarce houre in the day, are we free from encounters or preparation to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with thoſe <hi>Turks,</hi> Gods and our aduerſaries; thoſe vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Cantharides do ſwarme in the Mediteranean and Adriaticke Seas.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>Sex quoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die millia lampadum ante Pſeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do prophetae Mahometi tamulum, &amp;c. Petr. Beſſ.</p>
                  <p>Mr. R: Know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s in his Turkiſh Hiſtory.</p>
               </note> Millions of Chriſtian ſoules haue rued the terrour of thoſe (worſe then debauched <hi>Saracins</hi>) worſhippers of the falſe Prophet <hi>Mahomet,</hi> borne in an unluckie houre, whoſe body hangs up in their <hi>Sancta Sophia</hi> or chiefe Church of the City of <hi>Mecha,</hi> with ſix thouſand lamps alwayes burning before him.</p>
            <p>Theſe his followers and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers are and haue beene the ruine of many thouſand Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans on Land by warre, on Sea by pyracie.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:15631:16"/>Neglecta ſolent incendia ſumere vires.</q>
            <p>As fires neglected gather ſtrength, and make way for their owne fury: So doth their ſecurity giue advantage to our ruine and their cruelty. They have alreadie ſo long triumpht in miſchiefe, that if we credit the annals or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of ſuch who record it, they have got a greater part of Chriſtendome than is left for to oppoſe them. Or if we beleeve but our owne experience and ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie probabilities,<note place="margin">Hiſt. de de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct. &amp; ruina Troiae</note> we may expect that ere long like <hi>Aegcon</hi> the <hi>Greekiſh</hi> Pyrat they will ſet upon the Navy Royall of <hi>Iupiter</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>God ſtirre up all Chriſtian Princes to unity amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and to unite their forces againſt this common enemie, herein would lye the ſafety of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15631:17"/> their owne Monarchies, and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of their owne Subjects: For now ſo many ſhippes, ſo many fights, and funerals both of men and loſſe of ſhippes if not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matcht, ſo many ſquadrons, and fleets, ſo many feinds and furies armed to deſtruction. One halfe houre is the loſſe of many a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians life and libertie. If they dye, their bodies want what yours en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, the charitable honour of a grave.</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Propertius.</note>Cuius honoratis oſſa vehuntur aquis.</q>
            <p>Yet thats the leaſt of ſorrows:<note place="margin">Rev. 20.13</note> for the Sea ſhall giue up her dead as well as the Land; The fiſh in the Sea as the wormes in the Land ſurrender all at the generall <hi>audit,</hi> if they live they live to libertie, and need the helpe of your pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; or to ſlavery and thraldome, and need the aſſiſtance of your
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15631:17"/> purſes to redeeme them from their worſe then Aegyptian thraldome and ſervitude under <hi>Pharaoh Neco</hi> King of Aegypt.<note place="margin">Exod. 5.9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Brethren, its one thing to ſpeak of <hi>Hanibal</hi> at Rome, and another to meet him in the field: its one thing to ſpeake of their miſeries in England, another thing to be lyable to them, or behold them abroad; they are but ſhadows of compaſſion that are wrung from men that behold the miſeries of ſlavery with other mens eyes, in compariſon of what would be if you beheld them with your own; and ſaw either what they had which they would willingly want; or what they wanted which they would willingly enjoy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Suave mari magno, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lucre.</note> ſaith the Poet, Its an excellent object to ſtand upon ſome Tower and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a battell in the Sea betweene
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15631:18"/> two ſhips, or a ſhoare betweene two Armies; But farre from any thoughts of pleaſure or content is it for ſuch as graple with their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries now upon ſuch diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages as uſually happen to ſuch as go downe into the deep.</p>
            <p>Sea-fights now are not as they were betweene the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Thracians,</hi> where they did end their quarrels with Darts and javelins,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.40.</note> or as betweene <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Goliah</hi> with ſlings and pibble ſtones; But with the roaring and rending Cannon, that except our ſhips and ſides were vengeance proofe of force there muſt be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of bloud, loſſe of ſhips, of men, their lives, their limbes, their liberties. There, Chriſtian is forc't to fight againſt Chriſtian,<note place="margin">Iſa. 19.2.</note> as Aegy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptian once did againſt Aegyptian.</p>
            <p>He that is a bondſlave againſt him that is a freeman, and thoſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15631:18"/> of our owne nation and houſhold are forced to bee our worſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.<note place="margin">Mat. 10.36</note> In theſe bitter and ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts eyther with ſhips or Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes. How many poore and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable captives are there that cry out unto their Country men, as <hi>Lyncus</hi> the Priſoner of <hi>Hercules</hi> did upon <hi>Andromada,</hi> ſeeing him in another ſhip; <hi>O Andromada,</hi>
               <note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt. Tro.</note> 
               <hi>ſave thy friend</hi> Lyncus, <hi>elſe I ſhall looſe my liberty, and thou thy friend.</hi> But alas 'tis worke enough for us to ſave our ſelves, or if wee could ouer-maſter our enemies, yet our hands are manacled as were the Iſraelites, that they might not fight againſt the Moa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites, nor Ammonites, nor Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites.<note place="margin">Deut. 2.5.</note> There's them that haue payd too deare at home, for da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage done to their adverſaries abroad.</p>
            <p>All euils of the Sea ſaid one, is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15631:19"/> leſſe than ſhipwracke,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 6.1.</note> but this euill of ſlauery ſay I, is worſe than that: and this euill haue I alſo ſeene under the Sunne, and to this one more, that Princes walke on foot,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10.7.</note> and vaſſals ride; the ſubiects and ſeruants of honourable and Chriſtian Princes walke on foot, when ſuch vaſſals are mounted upon the pampered and ietting Steeds of honour and ambition, and triumph in number and inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency.</p>
            <p>This alſo would teach a man to preferre <hi>Minerva</hi> before <hi>Mars,</hi> and a certaine peace before a doubtfull victory.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hiſt. Tro.</note>No indifferent man but would chooſe to live with <hi>Demo Gorgon</hi> in the Caves of <hi>Arcadie,</hi> and live the life of the ſtrickteſt Ancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, rather than to expoſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to theſe dangers, or if neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of employment doe call him
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15631:19"/> abroad, he will learne the ſecond clauſe of the Sea mans Letanie: <hi>From Battell, Murther, and from ſudden death, or lingering ſlavery; Good Lord deliver us.</hi> Certainely, there is not ordinary probability of eſcape for ſhips of indifferent force or burthen, except they bee delivered by his hand of power if they fight, of Providence if they meet not with their enemies; for they are mighty, we are weake; they are light and nimble, when we are dull and ſlow: we are men of peace when they are men of warre. They are many, wee but few, how can they chooſe but winne, and we but loſe the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,<note place="margin">Deut. 32.30.</note> unleſſe that God did encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage us, and diſcourage them; that one might put a thouſand, and ten thouſand to flight.</p>
            <p>Yet this is but the ſecond ſtem of danger, our enemies at ſea; the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15631:20"/> third followes which is worſe than both the other,<note place="margin">The third danger: Enemies aſhoare after our arrivall.</note> that is our enemies on the land after our ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivall.</p>
            <p>There is not more danger of our corporall enemies at ſea, than of ſpirituall aſhore. Fryers of all or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders &amp; diſorders, Monks, Prieſts, Ieſuites, Inquiſitors, theſe ſeaſe upon many a reformed Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, as the ravenous Vulture doth upon the helpleſſe Chicken that's ſcattered from the wings of the Hennes protection, as the Wolfe upon the Lambe, or as the greedy and eager Hound upon the helpleſſe and breathleſſe Hare.</p>
            <p>Oh that God had as faithfull ſervants, as the Divell hath Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, who like their Lord &amp; maſter goe ſeeking whom they may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.8.</note> Or that they were as ſure Gods friends as they are his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Their care and diligence
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15631:20"/> to gaine a Proſelyte is far greater than others to auoyd it:<note place="margin">Mat. 23.15</note> for how many men, trauellers by land, voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agers by Sea, after all other eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capes, by their bad Pilotage, come to make ſhipwracke both of faith and of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1 9.</note>
            </p>
            <q>Coelum non animum mutant qui trans mare currunt.<note place="margin">Horat.</note>
            </q>
            <p>Such as deſire to enioy the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of forraigne Countries, change not their minde, but their ayre, was once uſed as an ancient Adage. But now too many change their religion with their climate, and their God with both; yeelding to the ſubtile inſinuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ſerpentine perſwaſions of thoſe crafty Politicians, Wolves in ſheepes cloathing,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.5.</note> who ſend many men home to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15631:21"/> their native Country, laden with the vices, faſhions, corruptions, and opinions of thoſe Countries they have lived in, of thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons they have conuerſed with, of thoſe arguments they haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed of, who having loſt all ſhadowes of ſanctity, returne to their owne home like the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-beaten Barke of <hi>Athens,</hi> with never a Planke of the ſame wood they were firſt made of. All principles of Religion &amp; grounds of faith being quite obliterate and defac't, they ſtampt in a new mould, having not ſo much as the reliques of a reformed Chriſtian, or halfe lettered monuments of their former profeſſion; but like the Vane upon the Maſt, or Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-cocke on the ſteeple, are tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned about with the winde of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vaine doctrine.<note place="margin">Eph. 4.14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>They wander ſo farre, till <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:15631:21"/> like they looſe their ſpirituall chaſtity and virginity.<note place="margin">Gen. 34.1, 2. <hi>Quint. Curtius.</hi>
               </note> Did they but with <hi>Alexander,</hi> change their habit onely in every Country, who when he was in <hi>Perſia,</hi> was cloathed as a Perſian; in <hi>Parthia,</hi> a Parthian; in <hi>Greece,</hi> a Grecian; we could and would allow them the liberty of the ancient Diſtick,
<q>
                  <l>Si fueris Romae Romano vivito more,</l>
                  <l>Si fueris alibi vivito more loci.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But too many turne Romans in heart as well as in habit:<note place="margin">Luke 22.55.</note> and while they are in the high Prieſts Hall warming their hands, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to make themſelves fit and ſerviceable agents for their King and Country, they then coole their hearts, and ſucke in the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy dregs of forraigne opinions,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15631:22"/> ſplit their ſoules upon thoſe ſhelues of errour; enter into the houſe of <hi>Rimmon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kin. 5.18 Rom. 11.4 2 King. 23.13.</note> bow and bend the knees of their deuotion and affection to <hi>Baal,</hi> runne after their new inuented Gods and Goddeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as once offending <hi>Salomon,</hi> who bowed his knees to <hi>Aſhta. roth,</hi> the Goddeſſe of the <hi>Zidoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and ran after <hi>Milcom</hi> the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the <hi>Ammonites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Worſe than <hi>Alexander</hi> they change their habit, worſe than <hi>Scipio</hi> and <hi>Sertorius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Val. Max.</hi> 2 Tim. 4.10 Luk. 22.57. They that turne Turkes.</note> they coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit their religion: and which is worſt of all, like <hi>Peter</hi> they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, forſweare, forſake their Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. There's ſome aliue yet to be happy if they could imitate him in his teares as in his apoſtaſie, in the reluctancy of his ſorrow, as in the precipitancy of his zeale, who like <hi>Zeno</hi> the Athenian Philoſopher,<note place="margin">Dixit ſe nunquam foeliciori venio navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaſſe quam cum navis eius ſubmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafuit quia tempeſtas ida ſuae tranquilli tatis exiſtet cauſa. Plut in I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a. <hi>Pſal. 120.5. Gen 9.27.</hi>
               </note> pretend both happineſſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15631:22"/> in their ſhipwracke, both of their faith and conſcience; theſe are worthy of other mens teares, that have none of their owne to waſh away their woes while they are not conſtrained, but content to dwell in <hi>Meſech,</hi> and to haue their habitations in the Tents of <hi>Kedar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God perſwade every ſuch <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheth</hi> to returne to the Tents of <hi>Sem</hi> from whence they are revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>Are <hi>Abana</hi> and <hi>Pharphar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 5.8</note> Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> better than <hi>Iordan?</hi> No, let the curſe of your death-beds light upon mee, if I preferre not the ſtreames of our <hi>Iordan,</hi> the free and liberall uſe of the Goſpell, in peace and tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, before the Abana or Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phar of their religion or inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and which is more,<note place="margin">Iudg 8.2.</note> as <hi>Gideon</hi> ſaid to the Ephramites, I preferre
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15631:23"/> the gleanings of our Ephraim, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the vintage of their <hi>Abiezar,</hi> and far before it too, as <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> did preferre the ſmoake of <hi>Ithaca,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the immortality of the Gods: often wiſhing for the enjoyment of this our native freedome, with as great a deſire as ever <hi>David</hi> could wiſh for to drinke of the waters of the Well of <hi>Bethlem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam 23.15.</note> 
               <hi>Oh that one would give me to drink of the waters, &amp;c.</hi> And heartily ſaluting the ſight of our Engliſh ground with as much ioy as <hi>Achates</hi> and his confederates did their Italian
<q>
                  <l>—Humilem que videmus</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irg.</note>Italiam, Italiam primus concla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat Achates</l>
                  <l>Italiam Laeto ſocij clamore ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>He that hath eſcapt theſe triple
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15631:23"/> and triple crownd dangers of the Sea, enemies in the Sea, enemies a ſhore, muſt needs bee glad, <hi>becauſe hee is at reſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Text.</note> 
               <hi>and brought to the haven where hee would bee, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I and my floating Pariſhioners are not now to learne experience in any or all of theſe three dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, yet the ſtormes of our Sea are blowne over, the danger of our enemy is already paſt, the ſhare of the cunning Fowlers,<note place="margin">Pſ. 24.7.</note> who catch nothing but blinde Bats and Owles, is alſo broken, and we are delivered, and brought to the haven where we would be: Now wee live to praiſe our God for his goodneſſe, and to declare his wonders to the children of men. And in doing both to pay our vowes of thankfulneſſe in the midſt of our Ieruſalem,<note place="margin">Pſ. 116 16.</note> in the midſt of thy Church and congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15631:24"/> which ſtands as in the midſt of Sion; of which I have often ſaid and prayd as <hi>Lot</hi> did of <hi>Zoar;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 19.20</note> 
               <hi>Oh let my ſoule eſcape thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; Is it not a little one and my ſoule ſhall live?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies that provoke us to thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.</note>But ſo much of our danger that muſt bring us to awfulneſſe; now followes the mercy that muſt bring us to thankfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>After the ſtormes of diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſucceede the calmes of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, the ſmooth iſſue of rough progenitors. For a moment doth hee hide his face from us, but with everlaſting mercy hee doth embrace us.</p>
            <p>Looke we to the preſent Text, it reduces Gods mercy to two heads, that like <hi>Tanais</hi> and <hi>Volga,</hi> water the reſidue of our meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; <hi>He makes the ſtormes to ceaſe, and bringeth them to the haven where they would be;</hi> two favours
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15631:24"/> that include all other favours in them.</p>
            <p>If brevity may bee any whet-ſtone to ſharpen your attention, or as holy water to ſprinckle on your face and awaken your devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I'le put them both in one, and exemplifie both theſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to us, by examples and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple teſtifications of his mercyes to others in the like miſeries, which are the beſt expreſſion of our owne ſorrows, or his fauours.</p>
            <p>Have you reade of <hi>Noah</hi> floating in his Arke without thought or feare of danger,<note place="margin">Gen. 7.17.</note>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 7.21.</note> when heauen and earth, the Sea and all that therein is, was in an uprore, when thouſands periſhed in that common innundation of euils. The caſe was ours, the mercy Gods, that wee alſo were deliue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red from thoſe ſurges wherein many periſh, and are brought to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15631:25"/> the Ararat of our deſires, to the hauen where we would be: <hi>O that men would, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 2.3.</note> Have you read of <hi>Moſes,</hi> craw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and ſprawling in his Arke and Barke of Bul-ruſhes, when the waves could not drowne him, nor Egyptian damage him.<note place="margin">Exod. 2.5.6.</note> We have beene as helpeleſſe as <hi>Moſes,</hi> and God as mercifull to us as unto him: he was to us inſtead of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raohs</hi> daughter, ready to challenge our cuſtody and protection. For by his mercy wee are brought to the haven where wee would be: <hi>O that men, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; 28.</note> Have you read of <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſafe convoy through thoſe ſeas wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thouſands after periſhed; the caſe is yet ours, wee have paſt thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>that coſt many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands both life and liberty, and are brought in ſafety to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>an of felicity, to the haven
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15631:25"/> where we would be: He was our Pillar and Cloud: <hi>O that men would therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Have you read of <hi>Daniels</hi> ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity amongſt thoſe Lyons that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward devoured his accuſers,<note place="margin">Dan. 6.23.24.</note> their wives and children; we have beene alſo even in the jawes of thoſe Lyons that have devoured many,<note place="margin">Turks. Pſal. 57 4. Pſal 3.7.</note> yet are we not delivered as a prey unto their teeth. But by the honourable convoy of his mercy, by the hand of his clemency, are wee brought to the haven where we would be. <hi>Oh that men would therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Have you heard and read of <hi>Ionah</hi> embarked, en wombed,<note place="margin">Ionah 1.17.</note> and entombed in the entrals of that great <hi>Leviathan,</hi> yet bleſſed with protection; Even wee alſo have had the like menaces of windes and waves, ſtormes and tempeſts, to make us fit morſels for thoſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15631:26"/> mountaines whoſe entrals and gorges would ſoone conſume us to a gelly.<note place="margin">Ionah 2.10</note> But the mercies of the God of <hi>Ionah</hi> are not yet di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed, for he hath brought us to the haven where we would be. <hi>Oh, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.24.</note>Laſtly, have you heard both of ſinners and Saviour both in one ſhip, covered with waves, toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with tempeſts; he aſleep, they awake; they fearefull, he power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; they as ſufferers, he as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander both of them, and what they feared. The caſe was ours, we have beene though not in <hi>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem nave,</hi> in the ſame ſhip, yet in <hi>codem praedicamento,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Toto ſonue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum aethere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mbi. Vir.</note> in the ſame predicament. And when we cride in our diſtreſſe, he heard us, when we went to awake him, he aroſe and calm'd the waves, ſtilled the windes, ſtayed the ſpouts, repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the guſts, rebuk't the ſtormes.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15631:26"/> And by his mercy are we brought to the Haven where wee would be. <hi>Oh that men would therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that neither ſlumbereth nor ſleepeth was our aide and helper, or if he have ſeem'd to ſleepe, tis as he expounds himſelfe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.<note place="margin">Cant. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>I ſleepe, but mine heart waketh:</hi> He ſeemes to uſe ſleepe but his heart waketh, and himſelfe is vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant for our protection.</p>
            <p>Once indeed aboue all other times he ſeem'd to us to ſleep out a miſerable and fearfull ſtorme, as if he had forſaken us, as once his Father had forſaken him, tis wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the file and records of eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie;<note place="margin">Mat. 27.46 In the mould of <hi>Genoa.</hi>
               </note> In <hi>Genoa</hi> the eight of Ianua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie laſt was ſuch a ſtorme and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt as cauſed the Inhabitants to rake up the urnes and bring forth the aſhes of the deceaſed Saint <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> as a propitiatory ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15631:27"/> to calme the raging Sea, I neither beleeve that they are, or that they are of ſome vertue, or that they have them if they were; yet there all the he Saints and ſhe Saints, Angels, Lords, and Ladies of Heaven were ſued unto, for mercy and deliverance.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 8.27.</note> In this never to bee forgotten miſery we cryed unto the Lord our God, who ſeemed to ſleepe and be awakened, and both the windes and ſea they did obey him. <hi>De profundis clamavi,</hi> out of the depth did I cry unto the Lord. <hi>Abyſſus abyſſum invocat,</hi> One depth calls on another, a depth of our miſery cauſed for a depth of his mercy; he did neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect us but for a while for the greater manifeſtation of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and increaſe of our ſervices. <hi>Oh that men would,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 99 6.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. Moſes, Aaron,</hi> and <hi>Samuel, Noah, Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niel,</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:15631:27"/> and <hi>Iob,</hi> thoſe ſpirituall Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers and favourites of the King of heaven in their diſtreſſes cried unto the Lord and hee heard them, and delivered them, and his mercies are renewed to us eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie morning, and his compaſſions faile not.<note place="margin">Lam 3.22. Pſal. 86.1.</note> He will have us know that when ſinners bow their hearts, he will bow and bend his eares to their prayers and ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations And that he deſires not the death of a ſinner, but rather, &amp;c. As I live, ſaith God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as I dye, ſaith God the Sonne, I deſire not nor delight not in the death of ſinners, no he is proner to mercy then to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. He was longer in deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one Citie, I, in threatning to deſtroy it, than in building of the whole world.<note place="margin">Ionah 3.4. Exod. 20.11.</note> Fortie dayes and <hi>Ninive</hi> ſhall be deſtroyed, ſixe dayes and the whole world was
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15631:28"/> made, the heaven, earth, the ſea, and all that therein is.</p>
            <p>Well may he forget to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with us,<note place="margin">Pſal. 30.5. Pſal. 136.1.</note> for the ſtormes of his anger endure but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment; but he can never forget to be mercifull, for the calmes of his mercy endures for ever. So much for the two generals, <hi>viz.</hi> the Dangers that provoke us to aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe; the Mercies that move us to thankfulneſſe:<note place="margin">3 General, Duties to draw us to obedience.</note> the third fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, which is duties to prouoke us to obedience. And this obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence muſt reflect backe againe, and be ſeene and ſhewed in the performance of a double dutie, <hi>viz.</hi> The publication of his prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and proclamation of his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.<note place="margin">Text.</note> 
               <hi>Oh that men would therefore praiſe the Lord for his goodneſſe, and declare the wonders that he doth for the children of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is all the Text will enjoyn
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15631:28"/> or the Prophet looke for, or the God of Text and Prophet require after the receit of his mercies, to yeeld unto him his tribute of praiſes. Tis as much as he doth aske, tis as little as we can give; tis his due and our duty. Of both which a word or two, and there cannot much more remaine. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto we haue but numbred the turrets and bulwarks of this text, as <hi>David</hi> wiſht the ſpectators of <hi>Sion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 48.1.</note> 
               <hi>Pſalme</hi> 48. and haue beene ſtayed <hi>in Atrio templi,</hi> in the porch entrance and body of the Text. Now ſuffer me to leade you by the hand into the ſanctuary of <hi>Sanctum ſanctorum,</hi> or holy of holyes. He that will not lend an eare, deſerues not that euery An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell ſhould moue a wing, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend the ladder, or looke out of the windows of heaven to aſſiſt him either in his wants or wiſhes.<note place="margin">Gen. 28.12</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:15631:29"/>
            <p>The firſt piece of our obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſiſts in the publication of his praiſes, and to do this brings honour to God: <hi>He that offereth me praiſe he honoureth me.</hi> Pſal. 50.23. The ſecond is the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his wonders, and he that doth not this, draws a curſe and propheticall anathema upon his owne head: which waits for ſuch as regard not the worke of the Lord, nor the operation of his hands. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 28.5.6. <hi>Oh that men would therefore praiſe the Lord for his goodneſſe, and declare, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe that haue beene moſt deeply intereſt in humaine miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and the receit of divine fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours are called here to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of theſe holy ſeruices: And they onely becauſe there cannot be a greater argument of Gods praiſe and our duty then eſcape from danger and receit of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15631:29"/> mercy. This truth is firmely built upon the pillars of the Text.</p>
            <p>The conquering <hi>Romans</hi> in all their honourable and glorious triumphs,<note place="margin">Hiſt. Rom.</note> ſuffered none to make any triumph, to erect any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phees, or to enter into the Temple of honour, where were Crowns, Garlands, Palms, Lawrels, Robes,<note place="margin">Aul. Gel.</note> Rewards, Emblemes; but they muſt firſt paſſe the Temple of vertue, where were Swords, Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velins, Targets, Lances, Helmets, and other inſtruments of warre, by which they muſt purchaſe their honour, and paſſe to their Temples: So reade we 2 <hi>Tim</hi> 2 5. <hi>Nemo coronabitur niſi qui Legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me certaverit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 7.</note> Reade alſo our vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of that bleſſed Saint, who were thoſe that were watching with crownes on their heads, Palmes in their hands, <hi>Haleluiahs</hi> in their tongues, adoration in
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15631:30"/> their hearts, long white robes on their ſhoulders, emblemes both of honour and victory. <hi>Hi ſunt qui venerunt ex tribulatione,</hi> Theſe haue come out of tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and have waſhed their robes in the bloud of the Lambe.<note place="margin">Rev. 7.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>They are fitteſt to be Heralds of divine praiſes, that haue beene the deepeſt intereſted in humane miſeries.</p>
            <p>Thus I haue long dranke of thoſe waters that are more bitter than the waters of <hi>Marah,</hi> more venemous than the waters of <hi>Nonacridis,</hi> are fitteſt to receiue that double fauour that <hi>Aſcha</hi> the wife of <hi>Othniel</hi> begged of <hi>Culel:</hi> The ſprings aboue,<note place="margin">Ioſh. 19.15</note> &amp; the ſprings beneath, bleſſings from heauen, and bleſſings from earth. They can but reliſh our bread and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah of heauen,<note place="margin">King 22</note> that haue long ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and dranke ſuch as <hi>Ahab</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:15631:30"/> threatened to <hi>Micaiah</hi> the bread of ſorrow and water of affliction.<note place="margin">1. King. 22.27.</note>
            </p>
            <p>They are moſt glad when they are brought to the haven,<note place="margin">Pſal. 107.25.</note> whoſe ſoules have moſt melted, and whoſe bodies have moſt ſuffered in the deepe and dangerous wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            <p>They are fitteſt for the calmes and favourable ayres of a merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hor.</hi> of the ſonnes of <hi>Dia. Sunt quos E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ea domu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reducet palma coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſiis.</hi> Thy ſons like hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly wights do come with an <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eon</hi> Garland home. 1. Cor. 9.24.</note> that have beene toſt and tumbled upon the ſurges and bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows of a mercileſſe ocean.</p>
            <p>In vaine ſhould the actors in the Olympian games have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed either their skill or abilities if they had not ſometimes retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned like the ſonnes of <hi>Diagoras</hi> with an <hi>Elcan</hi> palme and Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
            <p>In vaine ſhould we runne, if we ſhould not ſometimes get the Crowne.</p>
            <p>In vaine ſhould we wreſtle, if
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15631:31"/> not ſometimes get the maſtery.</p>
            <p>In vaine ſhould wee bee caſt downe into the deep, if not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times raiſed up againe to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and after long be brought to the haven where we would be. And in vaine ſhould wee bee brought to the haven where we would be, if we ſhould not praiſe the Lord for his goodneſſe, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 15.1</note>When God mercifully deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered <hi>Iſrael</hi> from the hand of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> and <hi>Aegyptian</hi> bondage, there followed a Song of praiſe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.</p>
            <p>When Chriſt mercifully deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered his Iſrael from the Egypt of ſin and iniquity,<note place="margin">Luk. 1.68.</note> there followed a ſong of bleſſing; Bleſſed be the Lord.<note place="margin">Iudg. 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>Deborah</hi> after her victory and <hi>Siſeraes</hi> ouerthrow may not ſleepe out ſuch a favour, nor ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber out ſuch a mercy. But <hi>Debo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:15631:31"/> muſt awake, and <hi>Baruke</hi> muſt ariſe to utter a ſong of triumph and victory, Awake, awake,<note place="margin">Exod. 17.14.</note> 
               <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borah. Moſes</hi> himſelfe after his conqueſt and <hi>Amalecks</hi> ruine, muſt write it in a booke for a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall, and rehearſe it in the eares of <hi>Ioſuah.</hi> Which he did and more, hee erects an Altar en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowls the mercy thereon, offers it with thanks, hallowes it with ſacrifice. This prieſtly Prophet and Propheticke King <hi>David,</hi> as he hath many Pſalmes of prayer to expreſſe his miſery; So hath he many of praiſe and thankſgiuing for the receit of mercy, witneſſe thoſe that he hath committed to the care of thoſe chiefe Muſitians, to <hi>Ieduthun,</hi> to <hi>Gittith,</hi> to <hi>Negi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noth,</hi> to <hi>Sheminith,</hi> and many more. Beſides theſe holy men of old neuer was there any age that wanted ſuch as did yeeld ample
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15631:32"/> and large teſtimony of their praiſe and thankfulneſſe, for the receit of bleſſings and benefits.<note place="margin">Caeſar.</note> All <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars</hi> actions ended in a triumph. <hi>Antonius Pius</hi> erects his Pillar,<note place="margin">Antonius Pius. Traian.</note> and <hi>Traian</hi> his, about which are engrauen their victories and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts: they both ſtand firme in <hi>Rome</hi> to this day. So ſhould all men that God hath bleſſed with deliuerance and victory, erect ſome pillar of thankfull remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and acknowledgement, that ſucceeding ages may be ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up to leaue the like monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of praiſe in the like deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, and beholding our good works may glorifie our Father which is in heauen.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>So was <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> animated the performance of many a noble action,<note place="margin">Val. Max.</note> by beholding the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs and trophies of <hi>Miltia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</hi> And <hi>Alexander</hi> ſeeing the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:15631:32"/> victories and conqueſts of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chilles</hi> engraven on his Tombe, was ſtirred up and provoked to an honourable emulation of the like valour and magnanimitie. I, and <hi>Caeſar</hi> when he ſaw the tombe of <hi>Alexander</hi> in the Temple of <hi>Hercules</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> and about the walls of the Church the conqueſts of the world, he wept to thinke how little he had done, and how much <hi>Alexander. In ea aetate qua iam terrarum orbem ſubegiſſet:</hi> It was worthy of <hi>Caeſars</hi> teares to conſider if he had done nothing in the time and age wherein <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> had conquered the world.</p>
            <p>Right even ſo may we (that will not be provoked by others patterns and examples, to a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of our gratitude) be compelled to weepe with <hi>Caeſar,</hi> while we ſee how the lives and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15631:33"/> acts of meere moraliſts do ſhame us beſides our owne.</p>
            <p>None of us but have received favours of an higher nature than any of them. But alas, where are our erected pillars? where are our Hecatombes? where our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locauſts? where the pyramides of our praiſes? where our ſmok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Altars? our burning Incenſe, our hallowed ſacrifices, our holy ſervices?<note place="margin">Gen. 31.47.</note> Tell me who with <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban</hi> hath erected a <hi>Iegar-ſaha du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha,</hi> a Pillar of witneſſe, betweene God and him, of Gods mercie, and his thankfulneſſe? Who with <hi>Iacob</hi> hath built an Altar of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement, and entituled it, <hi>El-elhoim Iſrael?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 33.20 Exod 17.14 16.</note> to ſhew that God is the God of Iſrael? Who with <hi>Moſes</hi> hath regiſtred the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours of his God and ruine of his enemies upon an Altar, and called the name of it <hi>Iehovah Niſsi?</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:15631:33"/> Who with <hi>Ionah</hi> diſgorged out of the bowels of the deepe hath erected his pillars of praiſe? His one for <hi>Ionahs</hi> two, which yet ſtand firme on the confines of <hi>Syriah,</hi> and are called by the name of <hi>Ionahs</hi> Pillars, or neare the place where the Fiſh ſet <hi>Ionah</hi> aſhore?</p>
            <p>Who with the holy woman hath powred out the oyntment of her beſt praiſes upon the head of her Saviour?<note place="margin">Mat. 26.7.</note> Or with the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that Chriſt cured of her bloudy iſſue, hath left a double monument one of her own miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, another of her Saviours mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,<note place="margin">Ioſeph. Ec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cl. Hiſt.</note> as we reade ſhe did in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Hiſtories.</p>
            <p>Who ſo is wiſe will ponder theſe things, and ſeeke to make ſome benefit by theſe examples which I lay before you,<note place="margin">Pſal. 107. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Iacob</hi> laied his Rodde of greene poplar
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15631:34"/> before the ſheepe of <hi>Laban,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 30.37.</note> when he layed ſpeckled Rods, they brought forth ſpeckled Lambes, but when hee layed fairer and white roddes they brought forth faire and white lambes. I lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you not ſpeckled but fairer and candid examples, of which I ſay to you as <hi>Moſes</hi> concerning the building of the Tabernacle,<note place="margin">Exod. 25.9</note> 
               <hi>Fac ſecundum hoc exemplar.</hi> And as our Lord and Sauiour to the queſtioning Lawyer, <hi>Go thou and do ſo likewiſe.</hi> Whatſoeuer things haue vertues, in others will be no leſſe eminent in the imitatours. Wherefore then whatſoeuer things are honeſt,<note place="margin">Phil 4 8.</note> juſt, good, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, laudable, that follow, they will carry away a bleſſing.</p>
            <p>Shall the Iewes offer their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in ſacrifice in imitation of <hi>Abraham?</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. W. R. Hiſt.</note> Or <hi>Ageſsilaus</hi> King of <hi>Sparta,</hi> offer ſacrifice in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:15631:34"/> of <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> which was throwne off the Altar by the <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ban</hi> Lords in <hi>Aulis:</hi> And ſhall not we be prouoked by bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter examples to imitation, of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter actions?</p>
            <p>God requires neither trophies nor triumphs, ſacrifices nor burnt offerings of us though we receiue as great and greater mercies as our progenitors, who ſo teſtified their thankfulneſſe. He askes no more of us but to be thankfull, and to praiſe the Lord for his goodneſſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Well ſaid the ſeruants to the Prince and Peere of <hi>Syriah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 5.13.</note> to their Maſter <hi>Naaman,</hi> when they would prouoke him to follow the Prophets order and adviſe. If the Prophet had required ſome great thing of thee, wouldeſt thou not have done it? how much more, when he bids thee but waſh and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:15631:35"/> be cleane. So ſay I, if the Lord of Prophets ſhould require ſome great things of you, would ye not do it? How much rather, when he bids you to waſh your ſelues from the foule ſpots of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſſe and be cleane?</p>
            <p>Should God raiſe a Subſidie, and challenge but what is his owne, and require of you that are Lords both of Sea and Land, to reſigne your Lordſhips in the one, your intereſt in the other, your title to both. Of you Land Lords to give up your rents and revenues. Of you rich men to give away your wealth, of you poore men to give away your almes, of you Officers, to give away your fees, of you Servants to give away your earnings, of you Marriners to give away your dear bought wages: I know that this would be <hi>Dui us Sermo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 18.23</note> a harſh
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:15631:35"/> and unreaſonable requeſt. But <hi>quis requiſivit?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mic 6.3.</note> who hath required thoſe things at your hands? God hath not troubled you with ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, nor wearied you with offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings; no, the God of heaven hath another requeſt unto you, which you may not, you muſt not deny him; and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in Gods name, and I in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> name, Beſeech you Brethren by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God,<note place="margin">Ro 11.1.</note> that ye preſent your ſelves ſoules and bodies as a holy, living, and acceptable ſacrifice un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, for although the other were an unreaſonable, yet this is but your reaſonable ſervice, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caius Cotta</hi> that thankefull <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut. vit. Ro.</note> when hee would ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe truely gratefull to the Senate, hee gave them his ſoule, and his reaſon was, <hi>vita &amp; mors iura na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae ſunt;</hi> Life and death are the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:15631:36"/> rites of nature. We cannot better teſtifie our prayſes and gratulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, than by giving our ſoules un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our Maker, whoſe they are by creation and redemption, ſaying with the Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 41.5.</note> 
               <hi>Into thy hands O Lord I commend my ſpirit, for thou haſt redeemed mee, O Lord, thou God of truth. Ioſeph</hi> charged his brethren to bring with them their little Brother <hi>Benjamin,</hi> elſe they might all have beene left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde: So Chriſt our elder bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">Gen. 42.20.</note> chargeth us to bring with us our little brother <hi>Beniamin</hi> of thankfulneſſe, elſe all other ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are of no value.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Plut. in v. Theſ.</note>
               <hi>Aegeus,</hi> the Father of <hi>Theſeus,</hi> ſent his ſonne to graple with the Minotaure, and gave him one ſute of blacke ſailes, and another of white, to be hoyſed onely and worne in caſe he got the victory; which though he had got, yet he
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:15631:36"/> returnes home with the blacke ſailes he went out with; at ſight of which, his father threw himſelfe from the Sigean Promontory, where he expected his ſonnes ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivall. In which hiſtory is lively moralized the naturall diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of too many, who like <hi>Theſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Aethra</hi> &amp; <hi>Aegeus,</hi> after a happy voyage and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, doe returne with the blacke ſayles of ingratitude and unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.30.</note> and hereby grieue the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of their holy and heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by which they are ſealed unto the day of redemption: whereas if they did hoyſe the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did and white ſayles of gratulation and applauſe, they ſhould rejoyce both Angels and Cherubins that ſit upon the ſcaffold of heauen expecting our victory and happy arriuall.<note place="margin">Luk. 15.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now that we may aright bleſſe
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:15631:37"/> God for his mercyes, let us in praiſing of him, offer this ſoure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold ſacrifice. Firſt, let us offer the ſacrifice of charitable almes, as occaſion is offered to us. <hi>To doe good and diſtribute forget not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">He 13.16.</note> 
               <hi>for with ſuch a ſacrifice God is well pleaſed:</hi> I, hereby wee ſhall make our ſelues Creditors to God, and him a debtor to us.<note place="margin">Pro. 19.17</note> For hee that giueth unto the poore, len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the Lord: he that putteth his money into the banke of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſhall make plentifull returne in this world,<note place="margin">Luk. 18.10</note> an hundred fold, and in the world to come, life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting. Secondly, offer to God the ſacrifice of an humble peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and contrition, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.17. <hi>The ſacrifice of God is a troubled ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.17</note> 
               <hi>a broken and a contrite heart, O Lord thou wilt not, thou canſt not deſpiſe.</hi> While your hearts are thinking of your ſinnes, let your
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:15631:37"/> eyes be like the Pooles of <hi>Heſhbon</hi> by <hi>Bathrabim,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 7.4.</note> which were euer full of ſtanding water, to waſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thoſe ſoule ſpots, that ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage of <hi>Adams</hi> clay that reſts within us. Thirdly, lets ſacrifice our wils, and make a perfect and abſolute reſignation of them to the will of God, whether it be <hi>pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiendo</hi> or <hi>faciendo,</hi> by doing or ſuffering, by a patient ſufferance of what he inflicts, by an obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent yeeldance to what he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. In this we do no more then the Sonne of God and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the world, who ſubſcribed to the will of his Father.<note place="margin">Mat. 6.10,</note> 
               <hi>Not my will, but thy will be done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly, wee muſt ſacrifice our ſinnes if ever wee meane to bring any honour to God by yeelding him his praiſe. This ſinne offering or offering of ſinne is equally neceſſarie with
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:15631:38"/> them that went before. Even thoſe that are as neare to us as <hi>Iſaac</hi> was to <hi>Abraham,</hi> muſt be ſacrificed: thoſe that are as neare as our right eye or hand muſt be cut off,<note place="margin">Mat. 5 29.</note> puld out and offered.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.10</note>Sinne is an <hi>Hagar</hi> that muſt be thruſt out of doores, elſe <hi>Sarah</hi> our conſcience ſhall never be at reſt and quiet.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 5.4</note>Sinne is a <hi>Dagon</hi> whoſe necke muſt be broke upon the threſhold of repentance.<note place="margin">1 King 5.10.</note> Sinne is a <hi>Naaman</hi> that muſt be waſht in <hi>Iordan</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven times in the vermilion ſtreames of our Saviours ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, ſeventy times ſeven times.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.15.</note> Sinne is a <hi>Ionah</hi> that muſt bee throwne ouer boord; if ever we meane that the tempeſts of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance ſhall ceaſe, or be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by calmes of mercy. You that love your ſinnes as <hi>Iudah</hi> lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>Tamar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ge. 38.15.</note> to enjoy your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:15631:38"/> by them, as <hi>Saul</hi> loved <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> to get honour by them,<note place="margin">Ge. 30.36.</note> as <hi>Iacob</hi> loued <hi>Laban,</hi> to get wealth and riches by them: You muſt part with all, in all, or none at all. One legge in the ſtocks will hold faſt the whole body: one ſinne in the ſoule will hold faſt both body and ſoule.</p>
            <p>In vaine ſhall you praiſe God for his goodneſſe, if you diſpleaſe him with the continuance and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of ſinne and wickedneſſe. To what purpoſe will you offer to ſing Pſalmes of praiſe and thankſgiuing, if the noyſe of your ſinnes drowne the noyſe of your Pſalmes, as Drummes in the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of <hi>Molech</hi> did drowne the cry of the burning and tormented In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, or as the ringing of the Bels doth drowne the noyſe of the clocke.</p>
            <p>How dare ye profeſſe a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:15631:39"/> and loyaltie to the King and Crowne of heauen, if we nou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſh ſinne in our boſomes and hearts, a traytor both to him and us?<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.1</note> Or offer the ſacrifice of praiſe to pleaſe him, when we offer the ſacrifice of fooles to provoke him. This is the high way to enrage him, by whoſe power we are crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by whoſe providence we are preſerued, to ſend worſe judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon us then we have eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iud. 16.19.</note> Such as with <hi>Sampſon</hi> will ſleepe in ſinne as in the lappe of <hi>Dalilah,</hi> let them beware their locks.<note place="margin">Iudg. 5.26</note> Such as with <hi>Siſerah</hi> will ſhort in this <hi>Iael's</hi> tent, let them beware their liues. If you will boyſe ſayle in all weathers, who can deplore your ſhipwracke? If you will runne from <hi>Niniveh</hi> to <hi>Tarſhiſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iona. 1.3.</note> who will pitty you though you meet with a worſe
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:15631:39"/> ſtorme in your teeth than what you ſeeke to avoid?<note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtr. Tr.</note> So did <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damas</hi> that ſonne of <hi>Antenor,</hi> to auoid a ſtorme, runne under a rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous rocke that cruſht him and killed him. So did the wiſe of <hi>Lot</hi> eſcape the vengeance of <hi>Sodome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ge. 19.26.</note> yet continuing in her ſinne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured a worſe and more peculiar, to be turned into a pillar of ſalt. And ſo ſhall all ſuch as are not ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned by her example, but will wilfully ſplit themſelues upon the Rocke of their owne ſinnes, they are unworthy of my farther re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe or your farther attention. Such as will avoid both the ſinne and danger, muſt praiſe the Lord for his goodneſſe; And ſuch as will give unto their heavenly <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> his tributary due of praiſe muſt do it,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.21</note> by acknowledging him to bee a Lord: So ſaid <hi>Ieptha</hi> to the men of <hi>Gilead,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 11.9.</note> 
               <hi>If I fight for
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:15631:40"/> you againſt the children of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, ſhall I not be your head?</hi> As I ſay to all of you, whoſe faces ſeeme to congratulate this day, whoſe attentions ſeeme to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this doctrine; If he fight for us againſt our enemies, and deliuer us, ſhall not he be our Lord? Yes! Lets firſt acknowledge him, and ſecondly lets apply him, all the merits of his active and paſſiue obedience muſt be laid claime to by a peculiar and particular ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication: ſo did <hi>Thomas,</hi> who ſeemed to haue engroſſed him to himſelfe,<note place="margin">Ioh. 20.28</note> 
               <hi>My Lord and my God.</hi> Thirdly, by obeying him as a Lord, in mercy for feare we finde him to be a Lord in juſtice, Thoſe mine enemies that will not I ſhall rule over them,<note place="margin">Lu. 19.27.</note> bring them hither that I may ſlay them:<note place="margin">Heb. 10 31.</note> Its a fearfull thing to fall into the hands of the liuing Lord. Fourthly, lets praiſe
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:15631:40"/> him as the onely Lord of heaven and earth without a riuall. For his glory hee will not giue unto another, nor his praiſe to grauen Images.</p>
            <p>God in the frontiſpiece of his royall Law provokes, perſwades his people Iſrael to haue or ſerue no other Gods but him, becauſe he, and no other God but he,<note place="margin">Exod 20.1.2.</note> had brought them out of the Land of Aegypt, out of the houſe of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage. So let all ſuch as the Lord hath redeemed out of the hands of the enemie, praiſe him alone as their ſoveraigne Lord He that hath more than one God, or one Lord, hath neither God nor Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> told <hi>Darius</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quin. Cur.</note> offering to him halfe his kingdome that the Heaven had not two Sunnes, neither ſhould the Earth have two ſoveraignes.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:15631:41"/> One <hi>Alexander</hi> was enough for a world,<note place="margin">Val. Max.</note> one <hi>Phoenix</hi> enough for an age: <hi>Duos Alcibiades neque Attica neque Graecia tulit.</hi> Nor <hi>Greece</hi> nor <hi>Athens</hi> brought forth two <hi>Alcibiades. Sparta</hi> brought not forth two <hi>Lyſanders,</hi> nor the world two ſuch Lords.</p>
            <p>Let thoſe fiſhermen that know no better ſacrifice unto their nets, or <hi>Neptune,</hi> thoſe husbandmen unto their dunghill, or to <hi>Ceres</hi> for their corne; others to <hi>Bacchus</hi> for their wines, to <hi>Pallas</hi> for their oyles, to <hi>Apollo</hi> for their wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to <hi>Minerva</hi> for their peace. Let the <hi>Turks</hi> thank their <hi>Mahomet</hi> for protection; the <hi>Perſians</hi> go to their god <hi>Nergal</hi> for defence; the <hi>Hamathenſians,</hi> to <hi>Aſima</hi> for ſtrength; the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonians</hi> to <hi>Succobenoth</hi> for deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance:<note place="margin">Ier. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.13.</note> For according to the number of their countries are the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:15631:41"/> number of their gods. Let them and all <hi>Atheiſts</hi> go to their falſe and fooliſh Dieties; all Papiſts to their Saints; but let us go unto the Lord our God. <hi>Oh that men would therefore praiſe the Lord.</hi> Oh that they would either ceaſe to bee men, or being men, would never ceaſe to praiſe the Lord. Or yet if our tongues could be weary of the publication of his praiſes, yet let them be employed in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation of his wonders.</p>
            <p>Text. <hi>And declare the wonders that he doth for, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We men are put upon the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and taske of Angels. To publiſh his praiſes, and proclaime his wonders is the office and theame of the Hyerarchy of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, who are ever ſinging their divine Carols of praiſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing in the expreſſion of his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. Had I the tongue of men
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:15631:42"/> and Angels, you the eares and wings of Cherubins, wee could neither well enough nor ſoone enough extoll his praiſes, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe his wonders. Of both I may ſay as the Pſalmiſt ſaid before me; <hi>Who can expreſſe the noble acts of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 106.2</note> 
               <hi>or ſhew forth all his praiſe?</hi> Yet ſince the royall hand of heaven vouchſafe not onely to require, but requite our weake performances with acceptance; As we have begun with his prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſo let us go on a little alſo to declare the wonders that he doth for the children of men.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Duhartas.</hi> 1. day. The world's a booke in Folio writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten all with Gods great works in letters ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall.</note>This world is a booke in Folio wherein are written the workes and wonders of Gods omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent hand, the acts and monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our maker and preſerver in his owne proper characters; Not as Chriſt wrote when hee wrote in the duſt that ſpirituall
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:15631:42"/> paradox, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8, 8. But as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremiah</hi> ſpeakes in another caſe,<note place="margin">Ier. 17.1.</note> 
               <hi>Stylo ferreo in ungue Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantino:</hi> As with a penne of iron, and point of a diamond. Man is no other but a conciſe abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this booke of the world, and an intire Index to ſhew and point out the capital obſervations of the voluminous and maſſie pile.</p>
            <p>Would you ſee works of imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, he turnes you to the leaues and pages of Gods ſacred Oracle, the Conclave of holy Scripture. Would you ſee works of Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, no page in this booke of the world, no act in this great and high creation, but gives us occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. I call you not to a tedious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capitulation of what I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken before in the expreſſion of his wonders in the Sea, there are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough as yet remaine unrelated.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:15631:43"/> For it is above all creatures won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull, whether in regard of the ſcituation of it which is above the Land, and roares and rageth as if it would ſwallow up the earth, as the earth did <hi>Corah</hi> and his rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious traine.<note place="margin">Num. 16.32.</note> Yet he keeps it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his bounds with a <hi>Huc uſque,</hi> or a <hi>Ne plus ultra,</hi> thus farre ſhalt thou go, and no farther. Or upon the nature of her ebbes and flows,<note place="margin">Iob 38.11.</note> her fuls and wanes, her ſpring and neape tides; It hath puzled the wiſeſt Moraliſt, <hi>Q. Cur.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes onely that tis terrible,
<q>Fluxus refluxus maris terrorem incutit.</q> Or upon the innumerable num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of creatures that are within the bowels of that womb of moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture.<note place="margin">B. Hall.</note> There are thoſe living and moving Ilands the Whales, that for greatneſſe of body,<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.6</note> infinicy of number, variety of forms, ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:15631:43"/> of ſhape, are above our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion or expreſſion: Theſe dance, rowle, and tumble upon her fearefull billows. Or upon the wonderfull art of Navigation and ſayling, which now is grown ſo excellent and ſo common, that we ceaſe to beſtow more wonder on it. That the water, a creature of fidelity, ſhould firmely beare up all veſſels, from the ſhallop to the ſhip, from the ſmalleſt Caruel to the mightieſt and greateſt Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rack: and with the helpe of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious and favourable windes, convey them from climate to cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, from <hi>India</hi> in the Eaſt, to <hi>India</hi> in the Weſt, if it were to the Antipodes themſelues, to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and commodity of their far diſtant owners.</p>
            <p>It's recorded to be the anſwer of a Traveller to one asking him what he had ſeene in his <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:15631:44"/> journey: <hi>Credite mihi fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres, ego ibi faciem nullius vidi niſi tantum Epiſcopi, &amp;c.</hi> Beleeve me, brethren, I ſaw no face there, ſave the Biſhops. So if I were in a few words to give an accurat and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act account of my two or three yeares abſence, <hi>Credite mihi fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres, &amp;c.</hi> Beleeve me, brethren, I ſaw the face of none, ſave onely of him that is the Biſhop of our ſoules; For his face and Image is upon all the works of his hands, by Sea or Land. That looke how <hi>Phydias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Didac de la Vega, Iol.</note> the cunning Artificer, had ſo curiouſly engraven his pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture upon <hi>Minervaes</hi> ſhield, that none could look upon the ſhield, but he muſt looke upon the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of him that made it; for it could not be taken off without the ruine of the ſhield. Right even ſo (with reverence to the Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of heaven be it ſpoken) hath
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:15631:44"/> God, that great and cunning Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificer, of heaven engraved his picture upon all his workes, that none can looke beſide it, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond it, aboue it, or below it, all his workes do both ſpread his glory and proclaime his Dietie. Looke we upwards, <hi>The heavens declare the glory of God, and the firmament ſheweth his handy work.</hi> The heaven of heavens that rowls ſo gloriouſly both above our heads, &amp; apprehentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,<note place="margin">Act. 7.50.</note> is the royall palace and place of his reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, there is the Chamber of his preſence, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 123. There the guard chamber of Angels, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angels, and Cherubins, <hi>Matt.</hi> 24.36. There the lodging Chambers and many mantions of thoſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Courtiers, the glorified Saints; theſe do all declare the glory of God, and the firmament as an open Court or Hall for
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:15631:45"/> all commers, doth ſhew his handy worke. It would puzle a <hi>Roman</hi> Antiquary, or <hi>Perſian</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie, or the moſt curious indaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of Natures ſecrets, to ſhew the nature, number, order of the greater and leſſer lights and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns of heaven, the Sun, Moone, Starres, Plannets, windes, thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, lightenings, Meteors, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pors, which do there attend the pleaſure of the King of glory, and fulfill his words, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 104.8. While I thinke, ſpeake, or write of them, I muſt do it in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets language, <hi>Oh Lord how wonderfull art thou in all thy works, in wiſedome haſt thou made them all.</hi> Or if we looke downe from heaven which is his throne,<note place="margin">Act. 7.49.</note> to earth which is his footſtoole: even there alſo do wee ſee the image of his goodneſſe, For the earth is full of the goodneſſe of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:15631:45"/> the Lord, and ſo is the broad ſea alſo. Here we behold him in his goodneſſe and wiſedome, making one Country the helper and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſupporter of each others welfare. He makes one the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary to furniſh her neighbours with corne, another the Armory to furniſh the reſt with weapons, another the Piſcary to furniſh the reſt with fiſh: another the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury to furniſh the reſt with gold. As <hi>Spaine</hi> is famous for her Wines, <hi>Calabria</hi> and <hi>Apulia</hi> for their Oyles; <hi>Sicilia</hi> and <hi>Turky</hi> for their Corne; <hi>Newfound</hi> land for Fiſh; <hi>Greece</hi> for fruit; <hi>Italy</hi> for Armes; <hi>Ruſsia</hi> for Furres; <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry</hi> for Gold; <hi>England</hi> for all.</p>
            <p>Thoſe bleſſings that ſeverally make other Countries happy, are conſpired to meet in ours. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be by the proper commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of our owne native ſoyle, or
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:15631:46"/> by traffique and merchandize with others, or by both. He that travels fartheſt, may ſit downe by the waters of <hi>Babylon</hi> and weepe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 137.1</note> while hee remembreth this our matchleſſe Sion. O <hi>England,</hi> ſay I, happy for peace, happy for tranquillity, happy for a generall conflux of all happineſſe that can make either ſoule or body bleſſed;<note place="margin">Lu. 19.42.</note> miſerable only becauſe ſhe knows not her owne happineſſe. <hi>Oh that thou wouldeſt know in this thy day, the things that belong unto thy peace.</hi> So ſhould this peace reſt long within thy walles,<note place="margin">Pſal. 122.7.</note> and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe within thy Pallaces, and thou ſhouldeſt continue as thou art, the terror of thy foes, the glory of the world, the Mart of Nations. And thus while wee wonder or declare the wonders that God doth for the children of men,<note place="margin">Iſa. 25.1.</note> may we ſay with <hi>Eſay, Thou
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:15631:46"/> art my God and I will praiſe thee, for i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou haſt done wonderfull things.</hi> And with <hi>Moſes,<note place="margin">Exod. 15.11.</note> Who is a God like unto our God, fearfull in praiſes, doing wonders.</hi> And while we meditate of the works them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, let's reflect our contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive thoughts of Adoration upon that great <hi>Atlas</hi> of heaven, that ſupports them all with the two ſhoulders of his power and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh that men would therefore praiſe the Lord for his goodneſſe, and declare the wonders that he doth for the children of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I have waded tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the three generall parts of the Text; thus much onely for the literall ſignification: the tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologicall is briefly this.</p>
            <p>The Church of God is this ſhip toſſed upon the Ocean, tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled upon the unconſtant billows
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:15631:47"/> of this troubleſome world; labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with the boyſterous windes of oppoſition, oppoſed with the enemies of Gods grace and her peace; packt and poaſted from haven to haven, from countrey to countrey. Sometimes ſhe is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried downe to the deepe and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermoſt Hell, as in the times of <hi>Nero, Maximilian, Domitian,</hi> and other <hi>Romane</hi> Emperours, as alſo in the dayes of Queene <hi>Mary</hi> in <hi>England.</hi> Sometimes againe ſhe is lifted up into the heaven, by an happy and bleſſed tranquillity, as in the daies and times wherein we live, and the Goſpell flouriſheth.</p>
            <p>The holy Bible is her armorie and place of defence, and tis like the Tower of <hi>David. Cant.</hi> 4.4. In which are weapons ſhields and targets, for a thouſand, I, for ten thouſand thouſand valiant men.</p>
            <p>The Law as her fore-caſtle to
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:15631:47"/> them that went before, wherein was placed the chaſe-pieces and thundering Cannons of legall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities, diſcharged by her cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning markſ-men the Prophets and Patriarks, againſt the bulwarks of hereſie, and Babels of ſinne in all ages. The Goſpell is now our ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory and place of defence; and herein alſo are variety of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, which are not carnall but ſpirituall, and mighty through God to throw downe ſtrong holds, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4.5. Here is the Helmet of ſalvation, the ſhield of faith, and Breaſt plate of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, the Sword of the Spirit which is the Word of God. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.13. which will quench the fiery darts of the devill, that <hi>like a roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lyon goes about ſeeking whom he may devoure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this ſhippe of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church ſits the ſoveraigne Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:15631:48"/> of our Lord and King as ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame head and governour, his Nobles, Lords, Iudges, Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, as repreſentative pieces of his owne Majeſtie, ſit in the ſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of eſtate, and to them is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the helme of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>His reverend Clergie of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees are each of them another <hi>Palenurus,</hi> or all Pilots guiding you in the right and perfect way, informing your judgements, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming your lives according to the card and compaſſe of Gods holy Word.</p>
            <p>The many promiſes of mercy, patternes of mercy, precepts of mercy, preſidents of mercy, are as ſo many favourable gales and windes to further us till we come to the end of our faith, the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our ſoules.</p>
            <p>All men are embarked in this
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:15631:48"/> ſhip of the Church, whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended voyage is to the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> but not all alike; Some as paſſengers receive neither wages nor content in this tedious and troubleſome voyage, who deſire a quicke and ſpeedy paſſage thorow this Baca of feares, this Bochim of teares, and with Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to be diſſolved and to be with Chriſt, which is beſt of all.</p>
            <p>Others as Marriners in their owne proper element, know of no other happineſſe, ayme at no other felicity, than what the ſea of this world affordeth them. The longer they ſtay, the greater their pay: they have their portion here in this life, and in the other, they receive onely the wages which is due unto them; it were better they were without it; for the wages of ſinne due to the ſervants of ſinne, is death both of body and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:15631:49"/> ſoule, when the former receive onely the gift of God, which is eternall life. I had rather ſtand to his courteſie, than engage him to payment:</p>
            <p>Before we can arrive at our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan of felicity, our Port and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of heaven, wee muſt all paſſe through the ſtraits of the laſt judgement. For wee muſt all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before his iudgment ſent,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.10.</note> to ſtand to our triall at the univerſall inquiſition, and then arrive at our deſired haven, where for ever we ſhall ſpend our dayes in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Lord for his goodneſſe, and in declaring his wonders to us the children of men.</p>
            <p>Angels ſhall meet us with our Palmes, our Robes, our Crownes; Arch-angels with tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs and Carols of Coeleſtiall bliſſe, and while we are thus ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our praiſes to the King of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:15631:49"/> glory, the whole hoſt and Quire of heaven ſhall ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſo much for the literall and hiſtoricall meaning of the words. Pardon my willing errour of tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, Polulogie is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fault of travellers, my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire was this day to pay my vows, where I am moſt obliged, and to whom, and before whom; and to erect this Sermon as a Pillar of thankfulneſſe, and an Altar of praiſe, that like the Prayers and Almes of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> might reach up to heaven. I ſhould be ſorry it ſhould proove a <hi>Babel</hi> to breede confuſion eyther in your patience or your memory.</p>
            <p>About this pillar are written theſe three things; Dangers, to draw us to awfulnes; Mercies, to draw us to thanfulneſſe; Duties, to draw us to obedience. And but three, as being moſt portable
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:15631:50"/> for your memory, eaſie for your judgement, ready for your uſe. Neyther is this Pillar of Prayſe dedicated as was that Athenian Altar, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.23. with this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, <hi>Ignoto Deo,</hi> to an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne God or Lord, but to a Lord of mercy, wiſedome and power, who knowes beſt, when, where, and how, to ſuccour and relieve us. Let this ſerve both for preſent uſe, and future memory. Thus if wee bleſſe God, hee will bleſſe us. Bleſſed therefore be the Lord God of Iſrael, for hee hath viſited and redeemed us his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>Let them whom the Lord hath redeemed from the hand of the enemy, praiſe the Lord: Let them that are daily ſpectators of his wonders in the deepe, praiſe the Lord, when they are brought to the haven where they would be.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:15631:50"/>
            <p>Let the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the houſe of <hi>Aaron</hi> accord in theſe holy and religious ſervices to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh his prayſes. And what ever o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doe or doe not; <hi>My ſoule praiſe thou the Lord, and forget not all his benefits, which ſaveth thy life from deſtruction, and crowneth thee with mercy and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kindneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lords holy name be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and praiſed from the riſing of the Sunne, to the going downe of the ſame, and let all the people preſent ſay, <hi>Amen. So be it.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:15631:51"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15631:51"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag. 4. lin. 24. reade leſt. 5. 16. Countries. 7 20. praiſe and thankfulneſſe. 8. 21. my firſt. 9. 2. what. 11. 4. and. ibid. 6. aires. 12. 3. if. 13. 10. after danger, reade, <hi>Scilla</hi> and <hi>Charib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis</hi> little injured by the Poets, in expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it's danger. 14. 17. ſpouts. 16. 15. ſo ſhould they. 35. 10. the ſeas: ibid. 24. this. 41. 10. us to. 42. 3. ſuch ibid. 5. their. ibid. 18. called. 45. 17. the. 47. 19. the. ibid. 11. walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. 48. 12. Thoſe that. ibid. 18. Caleb. ibid. 23. beſt reliſh the. 50. 5. both. 53. 15. that. 55. 7. at, 56. 15. beene vertuous.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:15631:52"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15631:52"/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Harper,</hi> 1634.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
